Guide to the Rufus B. Sage Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Rufus B. Sage papers
1778-1864
WA MSS 414
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
Sage, Rufus B., 1817-1893
Rufus B. Sage, 1817-1893
Rufus B. Sage left his home in Upper Middletown, Connecticut, in 1836 for Marietta, Ohio, where his sister Jerusha Sage Gear, lived. Except for the winter of 1837-38 when he was in West Virginia and made a voyage down the Ohio and Mississippi to Natchez and Fort Gibson, Sage spent most of the period between 1836 and 1840 in Marietta, Circleville, and Columbus, Ohio, where he engaged in the printing and newspaper business. In 1840, he decided to go to the Rocky Mountains and Oregon, and travelled with some friends to Independence, Missouri, to join a fur-trading party. The party left Independence on September 2, 1841, spent the winter in the mountains, returned to Independence, and went west again in 1842. By 1844, Sage was back in Ohio, editing The Whig Battering-Ram from August 9 to October 25 and preparing to write an account of his travels, which was published by Carey & Hart of Philadelphia in 1846 with the following title: Scenes in the Rocky Mountains, and in Oregon, California, New Mexico, Texas, and the Grand Prairies.
Scope and Contents
The Rufus B. Sage Papers include correspondence of Rufus B. Sage's grandfather Elisha Sage, his father Rufus Sage, and other members of the family, concerning the family's personal affairs and life in Connecticut, 1789-1828. In addition, the collection consists of letters and papers of Rufus B. Sage about his life in Ohio, his travels in the West and the publication of his book, Scenes in the Rocky Mountains, and in Oregon, California, New Mexico, Texas, and the Grand Prairies.
One of the original poems in the collection, "Night on the Prairie," is printed in Scenes in the Rocky Mountains.
The collection consists of 108 letters and papers, 268 pages in all.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
West (U.S.) -- Description and travel; Gear, Frances S.; Gear, Jerusha S, 1806-; Sage, Edmund, 1804-; Sage, Elisha, 1755-1801; Sage, Jerusha Butler; Sage, Rufus, 1777-1826; Sage, Rufus B., 1817-1893; Carey & Hart; Sage family
- Papers, 1789-1864
  Scope and Contents
  The family papers include correspondence of Rufus B. Sage's grandfather Elisha Sage, his father Rufus Sage, and other members of the family, about their personal affairs and life in Connecticut, 1789-1828; and the following letters and papers of Rufus B. Sage about his life in Ohio, his travels in the West and the publication of his book.
  - [Photocopies of previous organizational scheme] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Genealogical Record (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings concerning Rufus B. Sage's Three Years in the Rockies. 11 clippings. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - BEARDSLEE, NEZEKIAH [?]. Letter to Elisha Sage. 1pp., February 15, 1778. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - BUTLER, CHARLES W. Poem: "My Mother's Grave". Undated. 1pp. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CAREY & HART. 14 letters to R. B. Sage. 19 pp., April 7, 1846-March 15, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - DOWD, LEWIS B. Letter to R. B. Sage. 3 pp., July 24, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - GEAR, MRS. FRANCES S. Five letters to her brother, R. B. Sage. 11 pp., May 17, 1837- January 11, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - SAGE, MRS. JERUSHA BUTLER. Five letters to her son, R. B. Sage. 8 pp., July 3 [1836?]-August 25, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - GEAR, MRS. JERUSHA S. Letter to her brother, Elisha L. Sage. 1pp., March 3, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - GEAR, MRS. JERUSHA S. Nine letters to her brother, Rufus B. Sage. 25 pp., March 2, 1838-January 23, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - GEAR, MRS. JERUSHA S. Three letters to her mother, Mrs. Jerusha B. Sage. 9 pp., April 18, 1833-January 4, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - HEPBURN, JAMES, Pastor of the Second Baptist Church, Middletown. Certificate that notice of the intended marriage of Mr. Rufus B. Sage and Miss Marietta M. Miller was given publicly before the congregation, November 7, 1847. Upper Middletown. 1 p., November 29, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - MERWIN, WEALTHY SAGE. Letter to her cousin, R. B. Sage. 3 pp., July 25, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - MUNSON [?], THOMAS A. Two letters to R. B. Sage. 4 pp., August 16, 19, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - NASH, SIMEON. Letter to R. B. Sage. 2 pp., December 14, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - PAINE & BURGESS. Letter to R. B. Sage. 1 p., October 21, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - PIERCE, F. N. Letter to R. B. Sage. 3 pp., August 23, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - SAGE, ALVIN. Letter to his brother, Rufus Sage. 1 pp., April 12, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - SAGE, AMOS. Letter to his brother, Rufus Sage. 2 pp., February 21, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - SAGE, EDMUND. Seven letters to his brother, R. B. Sage. 13 pp., February 28, 1846- May 10, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - SAGE, ELISHA. Three letters to his wife. 4 pp., June 1, 1789-June 18, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - SAGE, ELIZABETH MARIA. Three letters to her uncle, R. B. Sage. 9 pp., August 23-November 13, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - SAGE, ELIZABETH WILLIAMS. Letter to her uncle, R. B. Sage. 3 pp., September 18, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - SAGE, FANNY. Letter to Hannah Jones. 1 pp., June 1, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - SAGE, GEORGE HUBBARD. Two letters to his uncle, R. B. Sage. 11 pp., August 16, 1863, September 20, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - SAGE, MARTHA. Letter to her mother, Mrs. Jerusha B. Sage. 2 pp., September 28, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. Letter to his brother, Amos Sage. 2 pp., 1814 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. Letter to his sister, Mrs. Francis S. Gear. 2 pp., November 5, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. Eight letters to his mother, Mrs. Jerusha B. Sage. 30 pp., June 19, 1836-September 12, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. Six letters to his mother, Mrs. Jerusha B. Sage. 26 pp., Spril 25, 1839-August 21, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. Six letters to his mother, Mrs. Jerusha B. Sage. 17 pp., July 20, 1842-January 1, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. Letter to his sister, Mrs. Jerusha S. Gear. 4 pp., May 22, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. Letter to Messrs. Paine & Burgess. 3 pp., October 25, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. "Description of the remains of an ancient fortification at Selsertown, eleven miles north of Natchez, Miss." 2 pp. 49 cm., 1838 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. Eight poems. 21 pp. 24½ - 42 cm., 1839-1842 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - SAGE, RUFUS B. Memorandum of accounts with Carey & Hart for the publication of Scenes in the Rocky Mountains. 6 pp. 12½ cm., 1846-1847 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - STEWARD, A. W. Letter to R. B. Sage. 1 p., August 19, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - WHITE, HENRY. Letter to R. B. Sage. 3 pp., January 7, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - WOODRUFF, A+S. Two letters to his sister, Mrs. Jerusha B. Sage. 8 pp., February 19, 1826-January 13, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - WOODRUFF, GEORGE R. Letter to his cousin, R. B. Sage. 3 pp., August 23, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 41)